Fadega Araya

Email: <a href="mailto:fadega.araya@gmail.com">fadega.araya@gmail.com</a>
website: <a href="mailto:www.fadega.com">www.fadega.com</a>

#### PERSONAL STATEMENT

A highly motivated, team player with over 6 years of IT experience focused mainly on web Technologies and striving hard to get associated with a progressive organization that gives better scope for updating knowledge and skill in accordance with the latest trends and be a part of a team that works dynamically towards the growth of the concern and gain satisfaction thereof.

I have excellent design & coding skills, as well as an ability to convert client requirements into exciting online applications.

#### CAREER ACHIEVEMENTS

- Promoted to management level as Education coordinator to craft and develop a curriculum and manage school finances (St. Andrews Refugee Services, Cairo, Egypt). (2016 2018)
- Developed a website for an Eritrean community radio broadcasted from U.S. which enabled the community members to engage and revive their culture in diaspora. (03/2017).
- Developed an Eritrean version of "who wants to be a millionaire" app which was used for a LIVE TV event on the occasion of Eritrea's 20 year independence anniversary. (05/2011)
- Along with three other fellow graduates, developed an artificially intelligent Text to Speech conversion System to covert Eritrean local language (Tigrigna to a Text). (08/2010)

# **Education and Training**

**University of Southern Queensland** 

Master of Computer Technology, July 2018 -Nov 2020

American University of Cairo, Cairo, Egypt

Certificate (pending) in Interpreting (CCIP), July-Sept 2017

YAT Learning, Cairo, Egypt

**Diploma** in Mobile Programming (Android), Oct – Dec 2016

University of Madras, Chennai, India (Correspondence)

MSc in Information Technology, July 2011 – June 2013

Eritrea Institute of Technology (EIT), Asmara, Eritrea

**BSc** in computer Science, Feb 2006 - August 2010

British Council, Asmara, Eritrea

Certificate in Strategic Communications, Jan-June 2010

International language and skill Tests (Exams)

TOEFL and GRE (Nov, 2012 and Feb, 2013 respectively)

# **Experience**

Web developer

Lethal Graphics, Perth, Australia - June-July 2018

- Developed websites in WordPress
- Tested and maintained web content for cross viewport display compatibility

#### Freelance web developer

Freelance work in web development - April 2015- present

- Developed websites from scratch(including <u>www.radioblina.org</u>, shalot.net)
- · Worked in maintaining the back end of stars-egypt.com

- · Partnered with alchemisesolutions.com to develop WordPress websites
- · Currently a member of a team working on www.blindictionary.com

### Interpreter and Translator (Freelancer)

#### International Organization for Migration, IOM - Aug 2014- Jan 2018

- · Interpret multiple Eritrean local languages to English and vice versa.
- · Translate migration related flyers and brochures from English to Tigrigna.

### **Education Coordinator**

# St. Andrew's Refugee Services (StARS), Sep 2016 - Feb 2018

- · Plan, administer and manage school terms and activities
- · Maintain and update school records and developing a curriculum
- Making decisions in an organizational capacity in matters of establishing partnerships with NGOs and other schools and liaising with partners for extracurricular activities
- · Supervising existing staff and recruiting new staff
- · Administrating school finances, writing fund proposals and reporting on budget

### Senior Teacher

### St. Andrew's Refugee Services (StARS), August 2015 - Sept 2016

- Took administrative responsibilities to assist the Education Program coordinator.
- Organizing CEP data for newly registered students and helping the coordinator in finding open spots.
- Engaged with parents on behalf of the coordinator unless there was an absolute need to meet the coordinator.
- · Taught science math, IT and science classes for high school students.

# Math/Science Teacher

### St. Andrew's Refugee Services (StARS), Nov 2014 - August 2015

- · Taught math, IT and science classes for Junior and high school students.
- Effectively used the student centered curricular system and audio visual training materials to successfully instill a burning desire to acquire practical knowledge.

## Interpreter and Translator (Freelancer)

### United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR), June 2014 - Aug 2014

· Worked as interpreter and translator on a daily contract basis.

#### Instructor

### El Wasila Institute of Science and Technology, Khartoum, Sudan, - April 2014

· Taught freshmen course in Information Technology.

#### Software developer and Team leader

### Eritrean Information Systems Agency (EISA), Asmara, Eritrea, Sept 2010 - June 2013

- · Led and monitored the software team at E.I.S.A,
- · Analyzed, designed, developed and tested software applications,
- · Analyzed and rectified software errors and present precise status reports on time,
- Designed and built applications using various programming languages (Java, C#, python, VB.NET...),
- Supported programmers and analysts to conceptualize and develop new software programs,
- · Planned software development lifecycle phases,
- · Researched and documented software users' requirements,
- · Offered input to SDLC documentation specialists and edited documentation,
- · Resolved programming issues by applying bug tracking methodologies.

# **Programing Language Lecturer (part-time)**

# Advanced Computer Tech, Asmara, Eritrea - July 2011- July 2012

 Lectured on programming languages namely Java, C# and VB.Net PLUS MS SQL Server, Networks installation and PC upgrading,

- Prepared new syllabus and evaluating the existing curriculum of the training institute,
- · Held practical labs for the networking and maintenance classes,
- Evaluation and assessment of the quality of the education provided at the institute.

#### ICT Teacher

#### Harnet Secondary School, Asmara, Eritrea, Sept 2008 - Feb 2009

- · Taught basic computer skills (MS office suite) to grades 10 and 11,
- · Introduced internet and emailing basics to students,
- · Prepared weekly lesson plans & prepared exams and quizzes,
- · Comprised discipline and grade reports in each term.

# **Skills**

### IT (Programming/Computer) Skills

*Operating Systems:* Linux: Debian and Ubuntu | Windows: XP to Win 10

**Programming Languages**: Java, C/C++, C#, VB.Net, python

Web Programming: PHP, JavaScript/React, HTML5, CSS3, jQuery

Web CMS: WordPress, Joomla

Shell Scripting: Bash

Databases/Network Administration: MS Access, My Sql

## Technologies and Development environments

- · Java + XML + JDBC + MySQL, GIT
- Apache + PHP +HTML5/XML + MySQL and Matlab

### Software tools and environments

- · Emacs, Make, Vi, Pico, Django, Flask,
- · Smart Draw, Microsoft Office Tools, Adobe Photoshop

### IDEs and frameworks

 Brackets, Sublime text, Visual Studio Code, React, Bootstrap, Django, Aptana studio, Flask and more

### **Interpersonal Skills**

- Excellent oral and written communication skills in many languages including English.
- Ability to adapt and work in a multicultural environment.
- Eager to continue education and learn through attending workshops, training, conferences, and independent study. Strong active listening, collaboration and coordination and facilitation skills with an eye for detail.
- Ability to work under pressure and meeting tight deadlines.

### Hobbies:

Playing guitar | Listening to Music | Watching movies | Reading Self-development books

#### References:

#### Amany Ahmed MA,

Education Director, St. Andrews Refugee Services (StARS) **Tel:** Mob: +201 002 058 59, Perth Time -6 (UTC+2)

Email: <u>aahmed@stars-egypt.org</u>

#### Redae T. Berakhi PhD

Teaching Assistant, University of Oklahoma

**Tel:** Mob: +14057382453 **Email:** redae.tesfamariam@gmail.com

#### Lee Reckman

<u>Director. Lethal Graphics</u> **Tel:** Mob: 0438 141 977

Email: info@lethalgraphics.com.au